<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="b" latest="yes">

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2010-02-01b.1WS.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="1WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200910/cmhansrd/cm100201/wmstext/100201m0001.htm#100201m0001.htm_dpthd0">
	HOME DEPARTMENT
</major-heading>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2010-02-01b.1WS.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="1WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200910/cmhansrd/cm100201/wmstext/100201m0001.htm#1002014000006">
	Control Orders (Lord Carlile's Fifth Report)
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2010-02-01b.1WS.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1648" speakername="Alan Johnson" speakeroffice="The Secretary of State for the Home Department" colnum="1WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200910/cmhansrd/cm100201/wmstext/100201m0001.htm#1002014000055">
	<p pid="b.1WS.2/1">In accordance with section 14(3), 14(4) and 14(5) of the Prevention of Terrorism Act 2005, Lord Carlile of Berriew QC has completed the report on the operation of the Act in 2009, which will be laid before the House today. I am also laying before the House the Government's memorandum to the House Affairs Committee on post-legislative scrutiny of the Act.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2010-02-01b.1WS.3" nospeaker="true" colnum="1WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200910/cmhansrd/cm100201/wmstext/100201m0001.htm#100201m0001.htm_dpthd1">
	JUSTICE
</major-heading>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2010-02-01b.1WS.4" nospeaker="true" colnum="1WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200910/cmhansrd/cm100201/wmstext/100201m0001.htm#1002014000007">
	Women's Diversionary Fund
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2010-02-01b.1WS.5" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1687" speakername="Maria Eagle" speakeroffice="The Minister of State, Department of Justice" colnum="1WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200910/cmhansrd/cm100201/wmstext/100201m0001.htm#1002014000056">
	<p pid="b.1WS.5/1">Two years ago I announced our commitment to a fundamental change in how the criminal justice system deals with women. In December last year we reported on the substantial progress made through the Government's strategy to divert women away from crime.</p>
	<p pid="b.1WS.5/2">Today, I am announcing the creation of a Women's Diversionary Fund, a &#163;2 million joint funding venture between the Ministry of Justice and the Corston Independent Funders' Coalition. The Women's Diversionary Fund will offer grants of up to two years and will assist us in consolidating good progress and in taking forward our strategy to divert women from crime, and reduce reoffending.</p>
	<p pid="b.1WS.5/3">This exciting partnership between the Ministry of Justice and the alliance of charitable trusts forming the coalition represents a commitment on both sides to transform further the way women are treated by the criminal justice system. By working together in this exceptional way we will build on the initiatives already announced.</p>
	<p pid="b.1WS.5/4">The fund will focus on:</p>
	<p pid="b.1WS.5/5" class="indent">service development or continuation, meeting gaps and further developing services; and</p>
	<p pid="b.1WS.5/6" class="indent">building organisational capacity.</p>
	<p pid="b.1WS.5/7">This new initiative will support further growth in community services for women and contribute to building the confidence of courts in alternatives to custody.</p>
</speech>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2010-02-01b.1WS.6" nospeaker="true" colnum="1WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200910/cmhansrd/cm100201/wmstext/100201m0001.htm#1002014000008">
	Interpreters (Expenditure)
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2010-02-01b.1WS.7" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1682" speakername="Bridget Prentice" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Justice" colnum="1WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200910/cmhansrd/cm100201/wmstext/100201m0001.htm#1002014000057">
	<p pid="b.1WS.7/1">Errors have been identified in the written answers given by the Minister of State, Ministry of Justice, my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1687" name="Maria Eagle">the Member for Liverpool, Garston (Maria Eagle)</phrase> to the hon. Members for Wycombe (Mr. Goodman) on <phrase class="date" code="2008-05-09">9 May 2008</phrase>, <phrase class="offrep" id="wrans/2008-05-09.1270"><i>Official Report</i>, c. 1270-71W</phrase> and for Romsey (Sandra Gidley) on <phrase class="date" code="2008-06-02">2 June 2008</phrase>, <phrase class="offrep" id="wrans/2008-06-02.640"><i>Official Report</i>, c. 640-41W</phrase> and by my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State for Justice and Lord Chancellor to <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1394" name="Dominic Grieve">the hon. and learned Member for Beaconsfield (Mr. Grieve)</phrase> on <phrase class="date" code="2009-03-16">16 March 2009</phrase>, <phrase class="offrep" id="wrans/2009-03-16.955"><i>Official Report</i>, c. 955-56W</phrase> and <phrase class="honfriend" id="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1379" name="Damian Green">the hon. Member for Ashford (Damian Green)</phrase> on <phrase class="date" code="2009-04-20">20 April 2009</phrase>, <phrase class="offrep" id="wrans/2009-04-20.337"><i>Official Report</i>, c. 337W</phrase> on the subject of interpreters expenditure.</p>
	<p pid="b.1WS.7/2">All the information the Ministry of Justice holds on interpreters expenditure is provided in the table below. I have written to the Members who received incomplete information and provided them with a full response.</p>
	<p pid="b.1WS.7/3">Expenditure on interpreters in England and Wales by the Department and its agencies:</p>
	<table>
		<tbody>
			<tr pid="b.1WS.7/6"> <td colspan="3"><i>The Expenditure for Financial Years 2007-08 and 2008-09</i></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.1WS.7/7"> <td></td> <td colspan="2"><i>To the nearest &#163;</i><i></i><i>000</i></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.1WS.7/8"> <td></td> <td><i>2008-09</i></td> <td><i>2007-08</i></td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.1WS.7/9"> <td>Ministry of Justice HQ</td> <td>26</td> <td>19</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.1WS.7/10"> <td>HM Courts Service (HMCS)</td> <td>638</td> <td>704</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.1WS.7/11"> <td>HMCS Crown Courts paid from Central Fund Budget</td> <td>4,503</td> <td>4,034</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.1WS.7/12"> <td>Tribunals Service</td> <td>5,283</td> <td>6,126</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.1WS.7/13"> <td>Office of the Public Guardian</td> <td>40</td> <td>40</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.1WS.7/14"> <td>National Offenders Management Service<sup>(1)</sup></td> <td>966</td> <td>868</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.1WS.7/15"> <td>Total</td> <td>11,456</td> <td>11,791</td> </tr>
			<tr pid="b.1WS.7/16"> <td colspan="3"><sup>(1)</sup> This figure includes translation costs as well as interpretation costs. The amounts are not separately recorded and can only be disaggregated at disproportionate costs.</td> </tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	<p pid="b.1WS.7/19">The information in the table excludes the following expenditure:</p>
	<p pid="b.1WS.7/20">It is not possible separately to identify expenditure on interpreters by magistrates courts from other magistrates court costs financed from the Central Fund Budget without incurring the disproportionate cost of examining every transaction, the supporting records for which are held locally. Sample exercises have been undertaken in the past to estimate the proportion of magistrates court expenditure that relates to interpreters but they have yielded inconsistent results.</p>
	<p pid="b.1WS.7/21">The NOMS figure excludes expenditure by the National Probation Service which is held locally by 42 probation boards and trusts who use separate and different accounting systems. Information could only be determined at disproportionate cost through examination of local records.</p>
	<p pid="b.1WS.7/22" class="italic">Suspects, charged individuals <i>and</i> victims</p>
	<p pid="b.1WS.7/23">Her Majesty's Courts Service meets interpreters' costs for victims, which are provided above. The police meet interpreters' costs for suspects and charged individuals. Police costs are funded by the Home Office.</p>
</speech>

<major-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2010-02-01b.2WS.0" nospeaker="true" colnum="2WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200910/cmhansrd/cm100201/wmstext/100201m0001.htm#100201m0001.htm_dpthd2">
	TRANSPORT
</major-heading>

<minor-heading id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2010-02-01b.2WS.1" nospeaker="true" colnum="2WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200910/cmhansrd/cm100201/wmstext/100201m0001.htm#1002014000009">
	Transport Security
</minor-heading>

<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/wms/2010-02-01b.2WS.2" speakerid="uk.org.publicwhip/member/1594" speakername="Paul Clark" speakeroffice="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Transport" colnum="2WS"  url="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200910/cmhansrd/cm100201/wmstext/100201m0001.htm#1002014000058">
	<p pid="b.2WS.2/1">My right hon. and noble Friend the Secretary of State for Transport, Lord Adonis, has made the following ministerial statement:</p>
	<p pid="b.2WS.2/2" class="indent">I would like to update the House on one of the specific decisions made by the Government following the recent review of aviation security-the introduction of advanced imaging technology (AIT), also known as body scanners at UK airports.</p>
	<p pid="b.2WS.2/3" class="indent">The requirement to deploy AIT machines at Heathrow and Manchester airports comes into effect today and I expect additional scanners to be deployed at these airports and to be introduced at Birmingham airport over the course of this month. This will be followed by a nationwide roll-out of scanners in the coming months. These scanners are designed to give airport security staff a much better chance of detecting explosives or other potentially harmful items hidden on a passenger's body.</p>
	<p pid="b.2WS.2/4" class="indent">The Department for Transport has introduced an interim code of practice covering privacy, health and safety, data protection and equality issues. The code will require airports to undertake scanning sensitively, having regard to the rights of passengers. This is available in the Libraries of both Houses and on the Department's website.</p>
	<p pid="b.2WS.2/5" class="indent">Given the current security threat level, the Government believe it essential to start introducing scanners immediately. However, I wish to consult widely on the long-term regime for their use, taking full account of the experience of the initial deployment. The Department will, therefore, shortly be launching a full public consultation on the requirements relating to the use of scanners as set out in the interim code of practice and will consider all representations carefully before preparing a final code of practice later in the year. I am grateful for the representations already received from the Equality and Human Rights Commission.</p>
	<p pid="b.2WS.2/6" class="indent">In the immediate future, only a small proportion of airline passengers will be selected for scanning. If a passenger is selected for scanning, and declines, they will not be permitted to fly. However, the interim code of practice stipulates:</p>
	<p pid="b.2WS.2/7" class="indent">&quot;Passengers must not be selected on the basis of personal characteristics, that is; on a basis that may constitute discrimination such as gender, age, race or ethnic origin&quot;.</p>
</speech>
</publicwhip>

